I wasn't asleep.
我并沒睡去
Just resting my eyes.
只是閉目養神而已
This is no time to be shy.
沒時間扭扭捏捏的
Tell Cromwell what Henry asked you.
告訴克倫威爾 亨利問了你什么
He asked me if I would look kindly on him.
他問我 是否欣賞他
If he wrote me a poem, for instance.
譬如 他若是為我作詩
I said I would.
我說我會的
Good.
很好
But if he attempts anything on your person...
但如果他對你有什么別的企圖...
..scream.
..你就大叫
What if nobody comes?
要是沒人來呢
Don't scream.
別大叫
Pray...
祈禱...
out loud.
大聲的祈禱
Something that will appeal to His Majesty's piety
去嘗試喚醒陛下的虔誠之心
and sense of honour.
和他的榮譽感
I'll get my prayer book.
我會去翻翻我的禱告書的
I'm sure I can find something that will fit the bill.
一定能找到些合適的語句
Thomas Cromwell, Secretary to the King.
托馬斯 克倫威爾 國王的首席秘書大臣
Show your colours!
表明你的來意
Tell him to let us in, before I show his arse my boot.
告訴他 放我們進去 別等我踢他屁股
Well...
好吧...
..how do I look?
..我看起來怎樣
That's why he sent you, isn't it?
這不就是他派你來的原因嗎
To see if I really am dying?
來看看我是不是真的快死了
He used to call me his flower.
他以前稱呼我為他的小花兒
When my first son was born, it was winter.
我的長子出生的時候 是冬天
There were no blooms to be had.
嚴寒時根本就沒有開花的植物
He gave me six dozen roses...
但他卻送了我七十二朵玫瑰...
..made of the purest white silk.
用最純白的絲綢包裹著
Over the years, I have given them to those who have done me some service.
這么多年 我把它們都送給那些曾服侍過我的人了
Will...
你...
Will you let the Princess Mary visit me?
你能讓瑪麗公主來看看我嗎
What harm can it do the King?
這不會對國王有什么傷害的
Chapuys has written to the lady Mary,
沙皮給瑪麗夫人寫了封信
saying that he can get her out of the country.
說他能把她帶出這個國家
Never!
不可能的
I answer for it with my life.
我用我的生命保證
What does Henry imagine?
亨利在想什么呢
Mary, returning with an army,
他覺得瑪麗會帶著一支軍隊回來
turning him out of his Kingdom?
把他從王位上趕下來嗎
It's laughable.
真是可笑
I answer for her intentions with my own person.
我可以親身為她的言行意向做擔保
Your own person has a lot to do, madam -
那你要做的事可多了 夫人
guaranteeing this, answering for that.
保證這個 擔保那個
You can only die once.
但您卻只可死一次的
And when I do...
當那時刻來臨時...
..I will set Henry an example,
..我將會為亨利作出榜樣的
for when his own time comes.
如何對待自己的死期
Do you think about the King's death a lot?
你經常想到國王之死嗎
I think about his afterlife.
我考慮的是他的余生
How is Boleyn's daughter?
那個博林家的女孩怎么樣了
She lost the child, I am told.
她的孩子流掉了 我聽說
I know how that is.
我知道那是什么樣的感覺
She and the King have hopes of another child, soon.
她和國王希望很快之后 再得一子
Particular hope,
是已經有了希望
or general hope?
還是將來會有點希望
My thoughts always confided in you.
我一直都很信任你的
I do hope there is no rift.
也希望我們之間不要有嫌隙
Well? Is she?
怎樣 她有了嗎
She's said nothing, still?
她還是什么都沒說
Of course, the wise woman says nothing
當然了 這女人聰明 什么都不會多言的
until she feels the quickening.
除非她真的能感受到胎動
Yes.
有了
She's been wrong before...
她之前一直弄錯了...
..but, yes.
..不過 終于有了
Does the King know?
國王知道了嗎
You should tell him. He might knight you on the spot.
你該去告訴他 他說不準會當場授予你爵位的
I suppose it's to be expected.
我覺得很有希望
She was with the King for much of the summer
她差不多整個夏天都和國王在一起
and when he wasn't with her, he would write her love letters
并且他不在她身邊時 還會寫情書給她
and sent them by the hand of Harry Norris.
由哈里 諾里斯親手送達
My lady, I must leave you.
夫人 我得告辭了
And you were usually such a good listener.
你之前可都是善于傾聽的人
The window was open.
窗子開著
He was such an innocent...
它是那么的純真無辜
What kind of monster would do such a thing?
什么樣的禽獸會做這種事
Perhaps he got up on the ledge somehow and...
也許它不知怎的自己爬上了窗臺
then his paws slipped.
然后爪子打滑了
- Paws slipped? Paws slipped? - Oh, get away, Mary!
- 爪子打滑 你說它爪子打滑    - 走開 瑪麗
Oh, yes -
哦 沒錯
I've re-baptised my fool.
我又給她重新受洗取名了
Well...
說起來...
the King's daughter is almost a dwarf, isn't she?
國王的女兒差不多是個侏儒 是吧
The French will have a shock if they ever see her.
法國人看見她 會震驚的
- They'll have a shock.- Yes.
- 他們肯定會震驚的  - 沒錯
I know they're trying for a match between her and the Dauphin.
我知道他們正試圖讓她與法國王子聯姻
While my own daughter...
而我自己的女兒...
I told you to go to France and negotiate her marriage.
我說過 讓你到法國去 商談一下她的聯姻之事
- But you said you were ill...- I was ill.
- 你卻說自己病了... - 我確實病了
You're never ill
你從未生過病
unless you want to be.
除非你在撒謊
And now the French laugh behind my back.
如今法國人都在背后笑話我
The French never intended a match.
法國人壓根就不想聯姻
It's as if my daughter had never been born.
我這女兒的出生簡直就是毫無意義的
As if Katherine was still Queen.
就好像凱瑟琳還依舊是王后
As if I didn't exist.
就好像我根本不存在
I won't let them make a royal match for Mary.
我不會允許瑪麗與王室聯姻的
I want you to visit her.
我要你去見見她
Take one of your handsome young men with you.
帶一個你家的帥小伙一同去
She's never had a compliment in her life -
她這輩子從沒受過什么贊譽
it shouldn't be hard to seduce her.
勾搭引誘她不會是什么難事
You want me to compromise her?
您希望她被破了處子身嗎
Do it yourself, if you want.
你要是想 自己上也可以
I heard she liked you.
我聽說她很鐘意你的
All that's needed is for her to make a fool of herself in public,
反正我只要她在大庭廣眾之下出丑
so she loses her reputation.
讓她名聲掃地
No.
不行
No? No?
不行 你竟然說不行
What?
你說什么
That's not my aim.
那不是我的目標
Those are not my methods.
我也不會用那些手段的
I know you're talking to the Seymours.
我知道你和西摩家關系甚密
You think it's a secret,
你以為這是個秘密
but nothing is secret from me.
但我卻是無所不知的
I can't believe you'd put your money on such a bad risk.
真是難以置信 你竟然把賭注全都壓在她身上
There was a time, madam, that you would listen to my advice.
夫人 有段時間內 您也對我言聽計從
Let me advise you now.
現在讓我再給您點建議好嗎
Drop your plans and schemes.
放棄你的所有計劃與圖謀吧
Put down the burden of them.
放下所有的包袱與負擔吧
Keep yourself in quietness, until your child is born.
低調行事做人 直到您的孩子出生
For Jane...
而簡呢
..she's a distraction, that's all.
她不過是個分心的瑣事而已
Let it run its course.
任她自生自滅去吧
- Pretend that you don't even see her... - He'll never abandon me.
- 假裝您從未見過她  - 他永不會棄我于不顧
Never.
永遠不會的
Since my coronation, there is a new England
從我的加冕禮之后 英格蘭就進入了嶄新的時代
and it can't subsist without me.
我不在的話 這個國家舉步維艱
I'm warning you...
我警告你...
..make terms with me, Cremuel...
在我的孩子出生前 克倫威爾
..before my child is born.
你最好和我達成共識
I hear you're going to put all the nuns and monks out on the road.
我聽說你要把所有的修女和修道士都趕出去
Monsieur Chapuys,
沙皮先生
wherever my commissioners go,
無論我的屬下們去哪
they meet monks and nuns who come to them, begging for their liberty -
都會有一大幫修道士和修女們圍著他們 乞求寬恕
and after the scandals I've heard, I'm not surprised.
聽到那些丑聞之后 我一點都不吃驚
Monks selling broken meats from the Last Supper to the poor.
修道士們將吃剩下的腐肉賣給窮人
Young novices being visited in their beds by older monks.
年輕的信徒被年長的修道士們造訪到了床上去
They claim they're living the "vita apostolica",
他們聲稱自己是"神圣使徒"
but you didn't find the apostles
但你找到的卻全都是
feeling each other's bollocks, did you?
互摸私處的信徒 對吧
Tell your master I mean good religion to increase, not wither.
去告訴你的主人 好的宗教應導人向善 而不是退化成獸性
I won't tell my master lies, if I tell him what I see.
我不會向主人撒謊 我只是稟實相告
I see discontent.
我看到的是不滿
I see famine, before the spring.
我看到嚴寒未過 饑荒四起
You're buying corn from the territories of the Emperor.
你們從帝國的領土上購買玉米
This trade could be stopped.
這些交易可是會被禁止的
What could your master possibly gain, by starving my countrymen?
把我國的民眾餓死了 對你的主人又有什么好處呢
He would gain this - he would see how evilly they are governed!
他能看到 這些愚昧的民眾是怎樣被殘酷統治的
Henry begins by mocking the Pope
亨利從藐視譏笑教皇開始
he will end up embracing...
終將一天會投身
..the devil.
惡魔的懷抱
Eustache...
尤斯塔斯
..what's happened?
到底發生了什么
What is this?
你這是怎么了
I have news from Kimbolton.
金博爾頓城堡傳來了消息
Queen Katherine...
凱瑟琳王后她...
She has only one or two days to live and I don't want her to...
她還剩一兩天的命了 我不想她...
Thomas, I don't want her to die alone,
托馬斯 我不想她孤獨死去
without anyone who loves her.
竟無愛她之人在側
And I'm afraid the King won't let me go.
恐怕國王也不會允許我去看她
Will you let me go?
那你會讓我去嗎
It would be a kindness
沙皮大使的拜訪探望
to let her have a visit from Ambassador Chapuys.
是對她的極大恩寵仁慈
Why?
為什么
So he can intrigue with her more conveniently?
這樣他就能更方便的和她密謀了嗎
Her doctors suggest, Madam, that she will very soon be in her grave.
夫人 她的醫生說 她已時日無多了
She'd fly out of it, shroud flapping,
她就算死了 也會裹著尸布飛出來的
if she thought she could cause me trouble.
來給我找找晦氣
Your Majesty, the Emperor may be a fond nephew,
陛下 羅馬皇帝也許是一個孝順的侄子
but he won't keep up the quarrel for a dead woman.
但他卻不會為了死去的女人和您永遠僵持的
This could mean the end to the threat of war - a new era.
這樣和解 對雙方都有好處 免除戰爭 進入和平新世紀
Ambassador Chapuys...
沙皮大使...
has never acknowledged my wife as Queen.
他從未承認過我的妻子是王后
Until he is prepared to bow before her, publicly,
除非他當眾拜見王后
there will be no diplomacy with that man.
否則我是不會接見他的
At last, God!
她終于是死了 感謝上帝
Not before time!
早就該死了
She's very much looking forward to seeing her younger brother
她可是非常想要見到她的弟弟呢
aren't you, dumpling?
是不是啊 小寶貝
And I share her impatience.
我也和她一樣的迫切
It has been a long enough wait.
我也已經等了好久了
I suppose we must expect the country to mourn for her.
我想全國民眾都要為她哀悼
She was once given the title of "Queen".
她畢竟也曾是王后之尊
Mistakenly.
她是錯誤的當上王后的
Majesty,
陛下
do you wish the body brought to St Paul's?
您是否要下令將尸體運送到圣保羅大教堂
We will lay her to rest in Peterborough.
將她安葬在彼得伯勒吧
It will cost less.
那樣花費少點
She sent me a letter.
她給我寄了一封信
I don't want it.
我不想看
Get rid of it, will you?
你處理掉 好嗎
Richard Rich says the King wants Katherine's plate and furs.
理查德 里奇說國王想收回凱瑟琳的餐具和皮革品
Rich had to point out that if she was never, in fact, his wife,
里奇說 如果她從未成為過他的妻子
he has no right to her property.
那他無權收回她的遺產
Oh, he'll have the furs.
噢 他會收回那些皮革的
"I commend unto you our daughter, Mary...
"我將我們的女兒瑪麗鄭重托付給你
..beseeching you to be a good father to her...
希望你能擔當起父親的責任
..and lastly,
最后
I make this vow...
我在此立誓
..that mine eyes desire you, above all things."
我在天堂之上 也會一直注視著你的作為"
If I'd been with you,
要是我在你身旁
I could have put you out of danger.
我一定不會讓你遇到危險的
I'd have beat it with a... with a blanket.
我會用毛毯馬上撲滅這火的
Oh, thank goodness that you...
謝天謝地 你...
If I'd been here...
要是我在就好了...
Leave it!
別弄了
Peace, my husband,
別緊張 我的丈夫
I am not harmed.
我沒有受傷
My Lady.
夫人
Let me drink this.
讓我先喝點東西
This was a good piece...
這帷幔本來是很好的...
Yes, what is it?
怎么了
Water must be kept at hand
手邊一定要備著水
and a woman appoin ted on every rota,
每個時段都要讓女仆輪番服侍
to check that all the lights are being extinguished.
保證所有的燈都徹底熄滅
I can't imagine how this could have happened.
無法想象這件事是怎么發生的
First, this is a household matter and not within your remit.
第一 這是內廷事務 不在你職權管轄范圍內
Second, she was in no danger.
第二 她安然無恙
Third, I don't know who lit the candle.
第三 我不知道誰點的那只蠟燭
Four, if I did, I wouldn't tell you.
第四 就算是我干的 我也不會告訴你
Five, no-one will tell you either.
第五 沒有人會告訴你是誰干的
If, as it may happen,
如果 如果發生了
some person visits the Queen after the lights are out...
某些人在熄燭之后 還潛入拜訪了王后...
..then it is an event over which we should draw a veil.
..那可是件我們要遮掩嚴密的大事了
Some person?
某些人
Some person, for the purposes of arson?
某些人 是為縱火而來的
Or the purposes of something else?
或是另有目的
Lady Rochford...
羅奇福德夫人...
Jane, when the time comes to unburden your conscience,
簡 等你放下你的良心包袱的時候
don't go to a priest.
不要去找牧師
He'll give you penance.
他只會讓你懺悔
I'll give you a reward.
而我卻會給你回報
How much does the lordship of Ripon bring in to the Archbishop?
里彭的貴族帶了多少錢貢獻給大主教
How much does Southwell bring in?
索斯威爾呢
Ha? I thought it would be more.
我以為會更多點呢
Majesty...
殿下...
..in the tournament, today?
..今天的比武上
If you should run against my son, Gregory,
如果您和我的兒子 格雷戈里 比試的話
will you forbear to unhorse him...
您會控制自己不把他摔下馬去嗎...
..if you can help it?
..如果能忍住的話
We can't help what we do, really.
我們做事常常都是情不自禁的 對吧
When you're thundering down at a man, you can't check.
當你對一個人雷霆出手的時候 你無法控制
It's a very rare event, you know, Crom...
真是一件罕見的事 你知道嗎 克倫
..to bring down your opponent.
..打倒敵手的時候
If you're concerned about what showing he'll make, you needn't be.
如果你是擔心他的表現 就大可不必了
He's very able.
他很有能力
I don't really mind what showing he makes.
我不在意他的表現
I just don't want him to be...
我只是不想讓他...
flattened.
受到打擊
You can't come.
你不來看比武了
Rafe is back.
拉夫回來了
I have to talk to him about some abbeys he's been surveying.
我要和他談談他正在調查的修道院
And there's my papers...
還有些文件要處理...
Richard will be here, to represent me.
理查德會在這的 代表我
It's my first joust.
這是我第一次比武
The Vatican has given Henry three months to return to obedience,
梵蒂岡給了亨利三個月的時間再度歸服
or the bull of excommunication against him
否則將他逐出教會的聲明
will be distributed through Europe.
將會傳遍歐洲
The Emperor's fleet is set for Algiers
羅馬皇帝的艦隊已經出發前往阿爾及爾
with 40,000 armed men.
率領四萬全副武裝的士兵
The Abbot of Fountains
方坦的修道院長
has been systematically robbing his own treasury,
一直在按計劃的清洗自己的財產
parliament opens in a fortnight.
議會還有兩周就要舉行了
The King says you're a credit to my house.
國王說你是我們家族里的榮耀
And you are.
你也當之無愧
Some years ago, before you were born,
好幾年前 還在你出生之前
I met an old Portuguese knight in Venice - one of those men
我在威尼斯遇到了一位葡萄牙老騎士
who made a career of riding to tournaments, throughout Europe.
他是專門在歐洲以騎馬比賽為生的人
I don't know... For what it's worth...
我不知道...不知道那話什么意思...
He said the secret to jousting was to sit easily in your saddle,
但他說比武的秘訣就是在你要輕輕松松的坐在馬鞍上
like you're going out to take some air.
就像是出門呼吸新鮮空氣一般
Carry your lance loose, until the very last moment
矛不要握的太緊 直到最后一刻在狠狠抓緊
and above all else...
最為重要的是...
..defeat your instincts to...
..戰勝你的求生保命的本能...
..survive.
..去戰斗
Well, you're ready.
很好 我想你已經準備好了
You look good.
你看上去很棒
Thank you.
謝謝你
Present.
禮物
You have to guess.
你猜一下是什么
St Appollonia's teeth?
圣阿波洛尼亞的牙嗎
No.
不是
Teeth from the comb of Mary Magdalene?
從抹大拉的瑪麗亞的墓里挖出的牙齒
St Edmund's nail parings.
是圣愛德蒙德的指甲碎屑
Tip them in with the rest.
將它和其余的指甲們放在一起吧
The man must have had 500 fingers.
這個人肯定是有幾百個手指頭了
What else?
還有什么事
The prior at Maiden Bradley claims he has a licence, under papal seal,
之前梅登 布拉德利聲稱她有羅馬的許可
allowing him to keep a whore.
允許他招妓
Westminster Abbey bought the bones of a dead elephant.
威斯敏斯特大教堂買了一頭大象的遺骨
Now, tell me what they wanted with...
現在告訴我他們想...
Gregory?
格雷戈里出事了嗎
It's the King, it's... it's Henry.
不 是國王 是亨利
He's dead.
他死了
The tournament hadn't begun.
比武還沒有開始
The King was running towards the ring and the horse just went down.
國王正騎馬跑向那個環 結果馬突然倒下了
No-one was near him, no-one to blame.
他當時身邊沒有一個人 所以也沒有人能受到責備
Master, if this is true...
學士 如果這是真的...
If he is dead...
如果他死了...
Should we escape now, before they block the ports?
我們現在要在他們封堵港口之前逃跑嗎
Fetch Fitzwilliam.
找菲茲威廉來
Move, move!
讓開 讓開
- Fetch a mirror to his lips. - It was tried.
- 把鏡子照照他嘴唇  - 已經試過了
What do you mean, leaving him lying here,
那你什么意思 就讓他躺在這里
untouched by Christian hands?!
不得基督的觸碰
By God, Cromwell - you're a dead man!
上帝啊 克倫威爾 - 你死定了
My Lord Norfolk, My Lord Norfolk! Where is the Queen?
諾爾福克大人 諾爾福克大人 王后在哪
On the floor.
在看臺上
I told her myself.
我已經親自告訴她了
My place to do it.
我的分內之事
She warned you to be obedient.
她警告你要聽話的
And now she's Regent, your days are finished!
現在她要攝政 你的好日子到頭了
No, no, no!
胡說八道
No woman with big belly as Regent.
沒人會讓一個大肚子女人攝政掌權的
Me! Me!
我才應該掌權
- Gregory!  - We've brought the Master Treasurer.
- 格雷戈里 - 財政大臣帶來了
Thank you, thank you.
謝謝你 謝謝
The Princess Mary - if she falls into Boleyn hands, she's dead.
瑪麗公主 如果她落入博林的手中 她必死無疑
We have to get up-country before this news does.
我們得在消息擴散前 快回城去
Go, Fitzwilliam. Go quickly.
快 菲茲威廉 快走
Mary's keepers are Boleyns. What if they won't yield her?
瑪麗受博林家的人監護 如果他們不放人怎么辦
Well, then she's dead.
那她必死無疑
We let her fall into the hands of the papists,
但如果我們讓她落到天主教徒的手上
they'll set her up as Queen - and I'm dead.
他們會擁護她為女王 我也會死
There'll be civil war.
還會爆發內戰
I don't know...
我不清楚...
A woman cannot rule, Cromwell! A woman cannot rule!
女人不能攝政 克倫威爾 女人不可以掌權的
Oh, my God, oh, my God.
噢 天吶 我的天
The King's breathing, the King's breathing!
陛下有呼吸了 陛下有呼吸了
Long live the King!
陛下萬壽無疆
Come on, come on.
挺住 加油
Come on... There you are, there you are!
挺住...醒了 醒了
There you are! Do you see me? That's it, that's it.
你挺過來了 你能看得見我嗎 太好了 沒事了
Get back, move away. Let him breathe!
散開 退開點 讓他喘口氣
Let him breathe, let him breathe.
讓他呼吸 讓他呼吸
How many men can say,
有多少人能說
"My only friend is the King of England?"
"我唯一的摯友是英格蘭的國王"
You'd think I have everything...
你可能認為我擁有一切...
..but take Henry away...
但如果亨利死了...
I don't know, Crom.
我不知道 克倫
You're not without support, you know?
你不是孤立無助的 知道嗎
Forgive my scepticism.
原諒我有所質疑
I mean, you would have support...
我是說 如果你需要支持...
..should you need it, against the Boleyns.
只要對抗博林家族 就能得到支持
Well, why should I need that?
可我為什么要支持呢
The Queen and I are perfect friends.
畢竟王后和我是完美搭檔
Forgive my scepticism.
原諒我有所質疑
This support...?
這種支持...
Sir Nicholas Carew says he thinks...
尼古拉斯 克洛爵士說...
you're an easy fellow to get on with.
他覺得你是個很容易相處的人
Does he?
是嗎
Perhaps...
也許...
Perhaps you should dine with him?
也許你可以和他一起進餐
What would have happened, Crom...
克倫 如果陛下沒能醒來...
if the king had not recovered?
會發生什么
Anne would have all, to rule herself.
安妮會不擇手段奪取大權
Though she'd have a fight with her Uncle Norfolk.
盡管她和她的叔夫諾爾福克爭執一番
Between the two of them, which one would I back?
他們兩方 我到底該支持誰呢
The lady, I think.
我覺得應該支持夫人
Let the lady be Regent
讓安妮夫人攝政
and the Boleyns will walk on our backs.
那么博林家族就會背棄我們
And your head will be on a spike.
你的頭會被掛在長釘上
But of course, that will come to pass anyway...
但當然 如果她能為國王誕下王子的話
if she gives Henry a son.
那這一切終將發生
My Lord...
陛下
I pray
我懇求您
the whole of England prays
全英格蘭都懇求您
that you will never joust again.
不要再參與馬上比武了
Why not geld me, while you're at it?
你騎在我上面的時候 怎么不干脆閹了我
That would suit you, wouldn't it, madam?
那樣你就順心多了吧 女士
The child had the appearance of a male
孩子看起來像是男嬰
and of about 15 weeks' gestation.
大概在孕期15周
What do you mean, "the appearance of?"
什么叫 "看起來像是男嬰"
I only repeat the words of the doctor...
我只是重復醫生的話...
Oh, get away with you, woman! You've never given birth.
滾開點 臭娘們 你又沒生過
What do you know?
你懂什么
There should've been a matron at her bedside -
她的床畔本該有侍女守著的
but oh, no
但是人呢
you Boleyns must all crowd in, whenever disaster strikes.
一有災禍降臨 你們博林家的人就蜂擁而至
I see that God will not give me male children.
看來上天不會賜予我小王子
If a king cannot have a son...
如果一個國王沒有嫡子傳承...
If he cannot give stability to his realm...
如果他不能給國家帶來穩定
..then it doesn't matter what else he can do.
那無論他做的任何事都毫無意義了
The victories...
戰爭之勝利...
the just laws...
法令之公正...
..the famous courts...
法庭之著名...
..nothing.
什么都無用
It seems to me...
在我看來...
that I was dishonestly led into this marriage.
好像是我自己不清不楚的就促成了這段婚姻
How...dishonestly?
怎么叫不清不楚...
It seems to me I was seduced...
我感覺像是被引誘了一般...
..practised upon...
或許是...
..perhaps with charms?
或許是魅力嗎
With spells? Women do such things.
用魔咒什么的 女人就是會做這樣的事的
And if that were so...
要是果真如此的話
..the marriage would be null, wouldn't it?
這段婚姻應該無效的 對嗎
"He sent her a purse - the King.
"國王 送給她一個錢袋
Christ knows how much was in it."
天知道里面裝了多少錢"
What did she do?
她作何反應
She sent it back.
她送還回去了
And the letter he sent with it?
隨錢包一起送的信呢
She didn't open it.
她沒有打開
But before she returned it...
但是退還前...
She kissed the seal.
她吻了一下信上的火漆印
Kissed it!
吻了它
What genius possessed her?
她可真是聰明啊
Now Henry's walking around, talking about "the virtuous and chaste Jane".
如今亨利四處談論 "善良賢惠的簡"
What do you say to that?
對此你怎么看
The game's changed, Cromwell.
局勢變了 克倫威爾
Now that Anne has failed again,
既然安妮又一次流產
it's possible that Henry may wish to remarry.
亨利很可能會再婚
As long as the King holds by the present Queen,
只要陛下還與現任王后保持婚姻關系
I will hold by her, too.
我也一樣會站在她這邊
So you have no interest of your own in this?
那你就沒考慮過自己的利益嗎
I represent the King's interests.
我代表國王的利益
That's what I'm for.
那是我存在的意義
My Lord Bishop,
主教大人
I hear you're leaving us for France?
我聽說你要動身去法國了
We shall miss you.
我們會想念你的
I went down to Putney...
我去了趟帕特尼...
..or to be accurate, I sent a servant. I learnt things about you.
..或者準確地說 我派了個仆從去 知道了一些關于你的事情
You've killed a man.
你曾殺了一個人
Not in this jurisdiction.
又不是在你的轄區內
Do your worst, Stephen.
你可真是劣性不改 斯蒂芬
Put your men on the road,
派你的人四處奔走
lay out money,
花錢打探消息
search Europe...
搜查整個歐洲...
You'll not find any talent I possess that England cannot use.
你只會發現我所有的技能才干 都是英格蘭所需要的
That lad you knifed in Putney died.
那個在帕特尼被你砍的家伙 死了
You did well to run, Cromwell.
辛虧你逃得早 克倫威爾
The family had a noose for you.
那個家族給你下了圈套
Your father...bought them off.
你的父親...用錢打發了他們
What?
什么
You see?
你看看
I know things about your life you don't know yourself.
我知道一些連你自己都不知道的事
I am disturbing you?
我打擾你了嗎
Eustache?
尤斯塔斯
No, I was just remembering.
不 我剛剛只是在回憶
Sit down.
請坐下吧
The cardinal used to tell people that I was an orphan...
紅衣主教大人過去常常告訴人們 我是一個孤兒...
..or else that...
...或者說...
I don't know... I was Irish.
我不知道...我是愛爾蘭人
Recently escaped from prison.
最近剛剛從監獄里逃出來
He said it was wise to deceive others about your past,
他說對別人欺瞞你的過去 才是明智的
even if there was nothing to conceal.
即使壓根沒什么可隱瞞的
But I was wondering...
但是我在想...
whether it's possible to deceive oneself.
是否有可能是在欺騙自己呢
About what?
關于什么
Something you believed about your life.
你所信仰的你的人生
Who you are...
你是誰
What you are.
是什么
You attended the funeral?
你參加了葬禮
I refused to.
我拒絕去了
She was not buried as a queen.
她并沒有以王后之尊下葬
I hear the concubine wore yellow, to celebrate Katherine's death?
我聽說那個姘頭穿了一身黃衣來慶賀凱瑟琳的死
She thought her passing would change her position.
她認為原配逝去 她的地位就能得到改善
So it may, but perhaps not in the way she thinks.
也許會變 但也可能不能如其所愿
There is talk about this "Semer" girl.
聽說有這么一個"西摩"的女孩
May I meet her?
我能見見她嗎
And here I thought you'd come just for my company.
我還以為你只是來陪我的
The lady you refer to is called "Seymour" -
你提到的這個女士叫"西摩"
and I'm surprised you take such an interest.
我很驚訝你竟然會對她感興趣
I would have thought you were more interested
我原本以為你可能更感興趣
in which French princess Henry will marry,
亨利要娶哪位法國的公主
should he dissolve his current arrangements.
他是否該取消當下的安排呢
Cremuel, you told me that was a fairy tale!
克倫威爾 你曾告訴我那只是個童話故事
You have expressed yourself a friend of my master.
你曾自稱是我主人的朋友
Tell me you won't countenance a French match?
別告訴我 你現在倒支持與法國的聯姻了嗎
I have influence on King Henry, Eustache...
我可以影響亨利國王 尤斯塔斯...
..but I do not claim to govern him.
..但我不會去控制他的
To succeed with Henry, you have to anticipate his desires.
為了和亨利相處 你就必須投其所好
But then...
接著然后...
..if he changes his mind...
..如果他改變心意...
..you stand out there...
..你站出來...
..expose, no?
...揭發他 不
It's Anne you should fear.
安娜才是你需要害怕的
She is desperate and dangerous.
她是不顧一切的 很危險
Strike first, before she strikes you.
先發制人 在她打壓你之前
Remember how she brought down Wolsey.
還記得她是怎么扳倒沃爾西的嗎
Perhaps you should come to mass, at court?
也許你應該到宮廷中來做彌撒
Cromwell!
克倫威爾!
You knew this was going to happen.
你早知道這種事會發生的
After all this time avoiding her,
回避她這么久
avoiding having to acknowledge her...
一直不愿意承認她
This will get back to the Emperor.
這些事都將會傳到皇帝陛下那去
Let's hope he will understand.
但愿他能理解吧
It had to be done, Eustache.
必須要做個了結的 尤斯塔斯
Why?
為什么
Princes do not think as other men do.
王子并不像常人一般思考
Now you have acknowledged his second marriage.
如今你承認了他的第二次婚姻
Now, if he likes...
現在只要他愿意
..he can let it go.
..他會就這樣放手的
When the Boleyns closed around him - poor fellow.
當博林家的人在他身邊時 可憐的家伙
Looked as if he was being carried off by slavers.
他看上去像是被奴隸商人拐走一樣
He didn't know what country he was going to wake up in.
他不知道他將在哪個國家醒過來
No more do I.
我也不知道
Let's go - find a crust to gnaw on somewhere - leave them to it.
我們去找別人聊聊吧 別管他們了
Cromwell?
克倫威爾
My master the Emperor hopes you will look kindly
我的主人 羅馬皇帝希望您能夠同意
on a Spanish match for Princess Mary.
瑪麗公主與西班牙聯姻
You presume too much, Chapuys!
你太自以為是了吧 沙皮
Do not presume to know my policy, ambassador!
別裝作你很了解我的原則 大使
So this was all a bargaining tool, was it?
就像是所謂的討價還價 是嗎
- Your Majesty... - You bow to my wife, then you send me the bill?
- 陛下... - 你向我的妻子鞠躬 然后現在向我來討債了是嗎
I have not forgotten how I helped your master against the French.
我并沒有忘記 我是如何幫助你的主人對抗法國的
He promised me territory -
他承諾會給我封地
next thing I hear, he's making a treaty with Francois!
接下來我便得知 他竟然和弗朗索瓦一世簽訂了條約
The Emperor treats me like an infant!
皇帝視我為兒戲
First he whips me, then he pets me, then he whips me again!
先舍棄我 又討好我 然后又再次舍棄我
Well, tell him I am not an infant!
告訴他 我不是個無知幼嬰
And tell him to keep out of my family business!
告訴他 不要多管我的私家事
First he tells me how I should marry,
先是干涉我和誰結婚
then he wants to show me how to deal with my own daughter!
現在又想干預我的女兒的婚姻
I demand a profound and public apology!
我要求一個正式 公開的道歉
I don't know what I'm supposed to apologise for!
我不知道我應該為了什么而道歉
I come here in good faith,
我是誠心誠意來這里
I'm tricked into meeting that creature face to face -
卻要和那個禽獸面對面
and then I'm attacked by Henry!
然后還要被亨利辱罵
He wants my master, he needs my master -
他想要我的主人 他需要我的主人
and instead, he plays these games!
可是他卻玩這樣的花招
Peace, peace.
放松 冷靜
We will do the apologising. Let him cool down.
我們會去道歉的 讓他平靜下來
- Never fear, we can keep the talks going... - Cromwell!
- 別緊張 我們會繼續商談下去的... - 克倫威爾
I know what you've done.
我知道你做了什么
You have gone too far in this matter.
這件事情你做的太過火了
You've made him promises, haven't you?
你對他保證了 是嗎
Well, you have no authority!
你壓根沒有任何權利做保證
You have put my honour in jeopardy!
你將我的名譽置于險地
What did I expect?
我在想些什么呢
What would a man like you know about the honour of princess?
像你這樣的人 怎么會知道公主的名譽有多重要
You've told him you have the king in your pocket?
你告訴他 你能把國王玩弄于股掌之間了嗎
Don't deny it!
不要否認
You would train me up, like one of your boys -
你整天像教育自己的孩子一般教育我
have me touch my cap when you come down in the morning
讓我在你每早下樓是 握帽致禮
and say "How do you, sir?"
然后和你說 "早安 先生"
Well, I really believe
我現在還真的相信了
you think you are the King...
你覺得自己才是真正的國王
and I am the blacksmith's boy!
而我才是鐵匠之子
Don't you?
你說是嗎
God preserve Your Majesty.
愿上帝保佑陛下
And now...
現在...
will you excuse me?
恕我失陪...
Cross your wrists.
交叉你的手腕
Like this.
像這樣
Get it in the water.
浸在水里
Keep your wrists crossed.
保持交叉的姿勢
Confuses the pain.
能減輕點疼痛
I trust a lesson has been learnt
我相信你已經得到了教訓
You are not a gentleman born.
你生來不是貴族
You should not meddle in affairs of those set above you.
你不該越權干涉你力不能及的事務
His Majesty may be pleased to bring you into his presence...
陛下可能會想要見你
Come, Wolsey! We're fetching you to Hell,
來吧 沃爾西 我們來接你進那個
where Beelzebub is expecting you to supper!
等你作餐的魔王們的地獄里去
But you should always remember who it was
但你應當永遠銘記
that placed you where he could see you.
自己的地位 得之于誰
From now on, remember who you serve.
從現在開始 請記住你是為誰而效忠
I shall profit from this lesson...
我從中 "受益匪淺"
I assure you, sir.
我向你保證 先生
See you do.
那就看你表現
And so...
所以...
Majesty, if it please you...
陛下 如果您覺得滿意...
Look favourably on the Emperor's overtures...
懇求您慎重考慮一下...
..we beg you.
羅馬皇帝的提議
For the sake of the realm and the commonweal.
為了國家和聯邦考慮一下
Well, if it's for the good of the commonweal, I...
如果真是為了聯邦著想的話 我...
I shall begin negotiations with Chapuys.
那我確實應該和沙皮去談判協商
I suppose I must swallow any personal insults I have received.
我猜我得對身邊所有的人都忍辱屈尊才行
Other topics will not be open for discussion.
其他的事先暫不考慮
The Emperor has discussed Mary with his own councillors.
羅馬皇帝同自己的議員們 談論了瑪麗的事
He'd like her married to his own relatives.
他希望她嫁給他的親戚
I will in no wise suffer her to leave this country,
除非她的言行舉止讓我無法忍受
until her behaviour to me is as it should be.
否則我絕不讓她離開英國受苦
Myself...
于我而言...
I'd go up-country -
我提議在國內為她選婿
and if she would not sign the oath,
但如果她不同意
I'd beat her head against the wall, till it were soft as a baked apple.
那我會好好的教育她 直到她順從屈服
Thank you for that, my Lord Norfolk.
多謝 諾爾福克閣下
Her mother's death is still raw with her.
她仍沉浸在她母親的去世之殤中
I have no doubt that she will see her duty,
我相信她會在接下來的幾周里
in these next weeks.
意識到自己肩負的責任
How pleasing to hear from you at last, Cromwell.
挺開心終于聽到你說話了 克倫威爾
Are we to assume that this new-found reticence of yours
我猜你今天的緘默
relates to yesterday's events?
是與昨天的事有關
When His Majesty, if I do recall correctly,
如果我沒記錯的話
administered a check to your ambition?
就是陛下揭露你野心的那件事
Thank you again, My Lord Wiltshire.
再次感謝 威爾特閣下
There will be no foreign match for Mary.
瑪麗不會遠嫁異國的
That is final.
務須多言
Will you walk with me?
陪我走走可好
I wish we would go down to the weald one day -
希望有一天我們能去草原上走走
talk to the ironmasters.
跟技藝高超的鐵匠們聊聊
I've had various drawings - mathematical drawings and advices...
我有很多圖紙 數理圖紙 還有很多建議規劃...
..concerning how our ordnance can be improved, but I...
一起探討如何改進我們的武器裝備 但我...
I can't...
我不能...
I can't make as much of it as you would.
我無法做到像你一般出色
It's because...
因為...
Well...
嗯...
Because you are my right hand, sir.
因為你是我的左膀右臂 閣下
So, shall we go down?
那么 還要不要一起繼續走走
You and I, meet the charcoal burners?
就咱倆 一起去看看那些鍋爐可好
Of course.
當然
But not this summer, sir.
但今夏就算了 陛下
I think you will be too busy.
我覺得你最近實在是太忙了
Yeah.
是啊
I cannot live as I have lived, Cromwell.
我不能再像以前那樣頹廢生活了 克倫威爾
You must free me from this...
你必須得幫我從安妮的魔爪中...
..from Anne.
解脫出去
Perhaps she and Harry Percy...
可能她跟哈里 珀西...
They were good as married, weren't they?
他倆關系好的就像夫妻一樣 不是么
And if that won't run, you know I was...
如果那不能奏效的話 你知道我...
I was, on occasion, with Anne's sister, Mary?
我曾偶爾和安妮的姐姐 瑪麗 相處...
Perhaps having been with kin so near...
可能走的確實是近了點...
Anyway...
不管怎樣...
I trust in your discretion and your skill.
我相信你的判斷力和能力
Be very secret.
務必秘密行事
Does not Mistress Seymour have the tiniest hands?
西摩小姐的雙手可真是小巧玲瓏
"Doesn't she have the tiniest hands?"
"她有沒有一雙小巧的手"
"Does she not have the whitest throat?"
"她有沒有最白皙的脖頸"
Has she not the wettest cunt you've ever groped?
她有沒有最濕滑的陰道
That's enough.
夠了夠了
Cromwell's spy is about.
周圍可是有克倫威爾的眼線耳目的
They talk about the Queen.
他們在非議王后
They?
他們是誰
Weston, Brereton...
威斯頓 布里頓
sometimes Norris.
諾里斯也時不時插嘴
Go on.
繼續說
The Queen needs to conceive another child, quickly.
王后需要盡快再懷上個孩子
And they say that Henry cannot be trusted to do the deed, so...
可他們卻說 亨利他 "不行"
one of them has to step in and do him a favour.
他們得"幫幫"他
Do they come to any conclusion?
他們討論出什么結論沒
They wouldn't really do it - none of them. It's just talk.
他們只是說說而已的吧 不會做什么的
So do they come to any conclusion?
那到底有沒有討論出結果
I think it's every man for himself.
我覺得他們都是各執己詞的
Well, I'm sure you're right.
我相信你說得對
Sounds like idle talk.
聽起來像是說大話
I don't think it will be necessary to use this...
我想你聽的這些話都不一定能派上用場
..but thank you, Rafe.
不過還是謝謝你 拉夫
Trouble is, Thomas...
問題關鍵是 托馬斯...
The King wants a new wife.
國王想另娶新歡
Fix him one.
就給他再找一個吧
I didn't...
我當初沒能如他愿
..and now I'm dead.
現在我就已經死了